<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pastors advocate. Together with the peoples monitor. By R. Junius Gent. Adde this as an appendix to Gods goodnesse and Englands unthankfulnesse. Imprimatur, Tho. Gataker.</title>
            <title>Englands unthankfulness striving with Gods goodness, for the victory. Appendix.</title>
            <author>Younge, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1230_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208886</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867803</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867803</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169474</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97255)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169474)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 169:E1230[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pastors advocate. Together with the peoples monitor. By R. Junius Gent. Adde this as an appendix to Gods goodnesse and Englands unthankfulnesse. Imprimatur, Tho. Gataker.</title>
                  <title>Englands unthankfulness striving with Gods goodness, for the victory. Appendix.</title>
                  <author>Younge, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Abraham Miller and are to be sold by James Crump in Little Bartholmewes Well-yard],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1651]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R. Junius = Richard Younge.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Intended as an appendix to Younge's Englands unthankfulness striving with Gods goodness, for the victory.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 19th. 1651".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Younge, Richard. --  Englands unthankfulness striving with Gods goodness, for the victory.</term>
               <term>God --  Goodness --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:169474:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Paſtors Advocate. Together with The Peoples MONITOR.</head>
            <byline>By <hi>R. Junius</hi> Gent.</byline>
            <head type="sub">Adde this as an <hi>Appendix</hi> to <hi>Gods goodneſſe</hi> and <hi>Englands unthankfulneſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Tho. Gataker.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>SECT. I.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in a <hi>Vine,</hi> what is taken away by pruning from the <hi>branches,</hi> is added unto the <hi>fruit:</hi> ſo ſpeech, ſaith <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch,</hi> is made more piercing, by taking away that which is ſuperfluous. And <hi>Seneca</hi> affirms, that inſtructions pointed with delight, pierce the more ſharply, and ſtick the more ſtedfaſtly. For which reaſons, in ſpeaking of this inſuing Subject, I will only preſent my Reader with ſome looſe <hi>Pearles,</hi> filed upon a ſtring; or a few <hi>skeins</hi> of fine <hi>Silk,</hi> cloſe wound up in <hi>bottoms;</hi> which perhaps with a good <hi>needle,</hi> I could have flouriſhed into a far larger Work.</p>
            <p>Nor need it offend any, that I more reſpect the weight and benefit of the <hi>matter,</hi> then the <hi>order</hi> of handling: Much <hi>Gold</hi> for a little <hi>Oare:</hi> Words and matter cloſe and ſweetly couched, was not wont to be mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, but better eſteemed.</p>
            <p>§. 2. There is a horrid ſin ſpread all over this <hi>Nation,</hi> and lies lurking in the hearts of almoſt who not? which hath not a ſecond like it; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>hinder</hi> the <hi>bleſſings,</hi> or <hi>draw down</hi> the <hi>curſes</hi> and <hi>judgements</hi> of <hi>God</hi> upon the whole <hi>Land.</hi> And yet men are ſo far from thinking it a ſin, that many (poſſeſt with a new ſtart-up <hi>white devil</hi>) think it a vertue. Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to contemn, rob and perſecute the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> who above all other men ſhould be honoured, reſpected, and rewarded. Of this ſin a few <hi>Notions, Aphoriſmes,</hi> or <hi>Concluſions.</hi> Only I wiſh thoſe whom it ſhall concern would hearken unto me, as they would have <hi>God</hi> another day hearken unto them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:169474:2"/>§. 3. <hi>Miniſters</hi> are our <hi>Paſtors,</hi> to feed us that depend upon them, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. They are <hi>Gods Husbandmen;</hi> to Till his <hi>Ground,</hi> and Sow his <hi>Seed,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.9. They are <hi>Watchmen;</hi> appointed by <hi>God</hi> to give us warning of inſuing danger, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.17. They are <hi>Diſpenſers</hi> of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and deliver to us nothing but what they receive from <hi>God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. They are the <hi>Stewards</hi> of <hi>Gods houſe;</hi> to give eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man his portion of meat, in due ſeaſon, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.42. They are the <hi>light of the world,</hi> and not only ſhine forth by a holy <hi>life,</hi> but inlighten us alſo by their heavenly <hi>doctrine,</hi> Matth. 5.14. They are <hi>the ſalt of the earth;</hi> to ſeaſon us with wholeſome inſtruction and exhortation, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.13. They are <hi>Maſter-builders;</hi> to edifie us the <hi>Houſe of God,</hi> and body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.10. They are our <hi>Captains;</hi> to <hi>fight Gods battels</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſpirituall enemies: and our <hi>Leaders</hi> to inſtruct us in the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Warfare,</hi> 2 Cor. 9.3, 4. They are <hi>Gods Embaſſadors;</hi> to declare his meſſage to us, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.20. They are <hi>Coworkers together with God,</hi> in converting and ſaving our ſouls, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9. And ſhould not theſe be honoured, reſpected, and rewarded? Yea how can that man have any intereſt in <hi>Chriſts bloud,</hi> who is not forced with admiration to ſay; <hi>How beautifull are the feet of them that preach the Goſpel of peace? bring glad tidings of good things, and publiſh ſalvation?</hi> Rom. 10.15. Iſa. 52.7. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> words are, <hi>Let them that labour in the word and doctrine, if they rule well, be accounted worthy of double honour,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.17.</p>
            <p>If men did but conſider, that they cannot be <hi>nouriſhed</hi> unto eternall life, but by the <hi>milk</hi> of the <hi>Word;</hi> they would rather deſire their <hi>bodies</hi> might be without <hi>ſouls,</hi> then their <hi>Churches</hi> without <hi>Preachers:</hi> And the <hi>devil</hi> that <hi>roaring lion,</hi> is more afraid of ſuch a ſilly <hi>Cock</hi> (a poor <hi>faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi>) then all the other <hi>great Beaſts.</hi> Yet I tremble to think how little they are regarded.</p>
            <p>§. 4. The <hi>twelve heads of Iſrael,</hi> as Reverend and Judicious Doctor <hi>Hall</hi> thinks, would never have written their names in their <hi>Rods</hi> ſo willingly, but in hope they might be choſen to the dignity of the <hi>Prieſthood.</hi> If they, all the <hi>Princes,</hi> had not thought it an high honour, been ambitious of the preſerment; they had never ſo much envied the <hi>Office of Aaron.</hi> What then ſhall we think of this change? Is the <hi>Evangelical Miniſtration</hi> of leſs worth then the <hi>Leviticall?</hi> Whiles the <hi>Teſtament</hi> is better, is the ſervice worſe? How is it that the great think themſelves too good for this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment? How is it that under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> men are diſparaged with that which honoured them under the <hi>Law?</hi> that their ambition and our ſcorn ſhould meet in one ſubject?</p>
            <p>§. 5. In <hi>Jeroboams</hi> time, <hi>the loweſt of the people were made Prieſts,</hi> (whom they reſemble that make <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> their <hi>Miniſters:</hi>) And now <hi>Prieſts</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> made the loweſt of the <hi>people!</hi> In all things the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is held the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>neſt of the Pariſh, till it comes to any <hi>Tax</hi> or <hi>Payment,</hi> and then they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169474:2"/>will honour him ſo farre, as to rank him with an <hi>Alderman.</hi> And what is the iſſue? they that would ſtudy <hi>Divinity</hi> above all <hi>other Arts;</hi> when they look upon the contempt, beggery, and vexation that the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> undergo, turn to <hi>Law, Phyſick, Trades,</hi> or any thing, rather then they will enter into this contemptible Calling.</p>
            <p>But O the ſordidneſs of ſuch! who think the term <hi>Miniſter</hi> contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible; when even <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, who muſt ſave them, if ever they be ſaved, cals himſelf a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> Matth. 20.28. But let them mock on, like thoſe ill-bred <hi>children</hi> to the <hi>Prophet,</hi> 2 King. 2.23, 24. <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſhall be Heir, when <hi>Iſhmael</hi> ſhall be turned out of doors. For as, <hi>He that deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the poor,</hi> (either in eſtate, or impotency of minde or body) <hi>despiſeth God that made him,</hi> Prov. 17.5. ſo he that deſpiſeth a man for being a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> or for the <hi>graces</hi> of <hi>God</hi> appearing in him, deſpiſeth, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt deſpighteth <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, and the very <hi>Spirit of God</hi> which made him ſo.</p>
            <p>§. 6. But ſecondly, they not only <hi>ſlight their Function,</hi> but they <hi>rob them of their maintenance:</hi> and that two wales: Firſt, Their <hi>Patrons</hi> (Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious and Atheiſticall <hi>Impropriators</hi>) rob them, perhaps of three parts of their livelihood, in carrying away the principall <hi>Tithes,</hi> for they have no more right thereunto, then to the Cloak on my back. Nor is this all; for many a curſed <hi>Patron,</hi> and pattern of <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> holds a <hi>Benifice</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant in his hands, till he hath ſounded many Chapmen, with a Who gives more? And then if <hi>Balaams Aſse</hi> can but dung him <hi>ſilver</hi> enough, he will ſell him all the ſouls in the Pariſh. For he looks more to the <hi>gifts of the hand,</hi> then to the <hi>gifts of the heart;</hi> and had rather loſe his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in <hi>Heaven,</hi> then let <hi>Chriſt</hi> have his inheritance on <hi>Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I need not tell you, that when <hi>Judas</hi> is the <hi>Patron, Simon Magus</hi> muſt be the <hi>Prieſt:</hi> Or if the <hi>Patron</hi> be a <hi>Formaliſt,</hi> or <hi>Good fellow,</hi> ſo muſt his <hi>Chaplain</hi> be. If the <hi>Chaplain</hi> be <hi>Papiſticall</hi> or <hi>Atheiſticall,</hi> his <hi>Clark</hi> muſt be ſo too: At leaſt if the <hi>Miniſter</hi> be conformable and <hi>Learned,</hi> it matters not though he be <hi>lewd.</hi> But let me give you this hint, That <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> with his <hi>Quid vos dabitis mihi</hi> on the one ſide, and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> with his <hi>Quid ego tibi dabe</hi> on the other ſide, make wicked bargains together. That ſuch <hi>Patrons</hi> as for lucre betray <hi>Chriſts flocks</hi> into the hands of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboams Prieſts,</hi> make as good bargains as <hi>Judas</hi> did, in <hi>ſelling his Maſter to the high Priests for thirty pieces of ſilver.</hi> Indeed one would think that <hi>Judas his halter</hi> ſhould make them afraid of <hi>Judas his queſtion:</hi> Or that all ſuch <hi>Patrons</hi> and <hi>Priests,</hi> ſhould be whip out of <hi>Gods houſe,</hi> which were happy for the whole <hi>Nation,</hi> though it were by far too ſmall a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For certainly, if the <hi>buyers and ſellers in the Temple,</hi> deſerved <hi>whipping,</hi> the buyers and ſellers of the <hi>Temple</hi> deſerve <hi>hanging,</hi> or worſe: As who knows whether they therefore ſcape correction here, that they may have the greater damnation hereafter?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:169474:3"/>§. 7. True, while they are <hi>drunk with avarice,</hi> and <hi>out of their wits</hi> with an ignorant <hi>partiality,</hi> they will maintain, and would fain perſwade their conſciences to think, that they have a right to the <hi>Churches maintenance.</hi> They gave good mony for it, or they had it from their <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> and they take but what the <hi>Law</hi> allows, that is, what their <hi>law,</hi> not what the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi> alows, or the <hi>ancient Laws of this Land:</hi> and yet they hope not to be ſaved by the <hi>Law</hi> but by the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> And let me but appeal, as <hi>Biſhop Groſtead</hi> did, from <hi>Pope Adrian</hi> private, to <hi>Pope Adrian</hi> publick, and not intereſted in the cauſe: Or as another, from his Paſſion as <hi>Clement,</hi> to his Holineſſe as <hi>Peter;</hi> even from them drunk, unto them come to themſelves, (which will be at leaſt upon their <hi>death beds, or in hell</hi>) they will ſee it to be a curſed <hi>ſacriledge, the worſt of all thefts or murthers;</hi> and that it were far better for <hi>Chriſt</hi> to have his inheritance in his own hands, then to ſtand to their courteſies, who had rather there were no <hi>Goſpel,</hi> nor <hi>Preacher</hi> in the <hi>world,</hi> then that their <hi>Heir</hi> ſhould want a <hi>Parſonage.</hi> But now, the <hi>melody</hi> of <hi>gain</hi> whiſtles out the <hi>eye of conſcience;</hi> ſo they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh it out on their luſts. As how often doth the <hi>Impropriator,</hi> ſome up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart Gallant, newly come to age, wear a <hi>Church upon his back,</hi> and the <hi>Bells at his heels</hi> gingling? while the <hi>Miniſter</hi> whom he robs, is forced to go in a thredbare Coat, and the poor <hi>Flock</hi> are <hi>ſtarved</hi> in the Country. So that the <hi>father</hi> moſt unjuſtly, with the ſpoils of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> purchaſeth <hi>fields of bloud,</hi> that the <hi>ſon</hi> may <hi>Belteſhazzar</hi> like, <hi>drink carowſes in the bowls of the Temple.</hi> But what is the iſſue? They that <hi>ſwollow Churches</hi> (like <hi>dogs</hi> that eat <hi>knotgraſſe</hi>) never thrive after it. Yea <hi>Church livings</hi> have been more unfortunate to the <hi>Gentry of England,</hi> then was the <hi>Gold of Tholoſſa</hi> to the <hi>followers of Scipio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 8. Again ſecondly, As the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is <hi>rob'd</hi> by his <hi>Patron,</hi> ſo he is <hi>gulled</hi> by his <hi>people;</hi> who if they can avoid it, will pay him nothing: or if there be no remedy, will give him the <hi>worſt of their younglings,</hi> and that <hi>by the halves.</hi> The people in <hi>Moſes</hi> time <hi>brought ſo much treaſury, and ſo many gifts to the building of Gods Tabernacle,</hi> that the <hi>Prieſts</hi> were fain to <hi>bid them ceaſe,</hi> Exod. 36.5, 6, 7. but men are now ſo ſparing of their pains and coſt, that they think that very time miſpent which is imployed in the ſervice of <hi>God;</hi> and that money ill beſtowed, which is given to the maintenance of his <hi>Miniſters.</hi> They uſe <hi>Preachers,</hi> in caſe they like them, as <hi>Carriers</hi> do their <hi>horſes;</hi> who lay <hi>heavy burthens</hi> upon their <hi>backs,</hi> and then hang <hi>bells at their ears</hi> to make them muſick: or rather, as <hi>Gentlemen</hi> uſe <hi>poſt horſes;</hi> whom they <hi>ſpur</hi> till they are <hi>ſpent,</hi> and then a <hi>freſh</hi> is called for. Mean while they ſit ſtill, and think to go to <hi>Heaven</hi> by giving them the hearing, which commonly is all they give them.</p>
            <p>It it <hi>Satans</hi> policie, that they that maintain the Truth, ſhould not have to maintain themſelves. And it is the pride of this <hi>ſacrilegious Age,</hi> that the <hi>Minister</hi> be alwaies the pooreſt in the <hi>Pariſh.</hi> They empty their <hi>Books,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:169474:3"/>they empty their <hi>veins,</hi> they empty their <hi>brains,</hi> but they muſt feed upon <hi>Turnips,</hi> and leave their <hi>poſterity beggers.</hi> Perhaps they will give a <hi>Miniſter</hi> great thanks, and if he be a witty man, that tickles their ears, and pleaſeth their ſenſe; they will extoll him to the <hi>skies.</hi> But men cannot <hi>Camelion</hi> like, live by the ayre of thanks, or feed ever the fatter for others praiſes.</p>
            <p>§ 9. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> complained, that in his time, the <hi>Levites</hi> for want of maintenance, were fain to leave the <hi>Temple,</hi> and follow the <hi>plow,</hi> Nehem. 13.10. And <hi>Luther</hi> of his Age; that this was the cauſe, why the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable of the <hi>Clergy</hi> beat their <hi>brains,</hi> and ſet their <hi>wits</hi> upon the <hi>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> to invent ſuch tricks of ſuperſtition, as might be advantagious to them, <hi>prayer for the dead, indulgences,</hi> &amp;c. For, ſaith he, when the <hi>covetouſneſs of the Prieſts,</hi> and the <hi>ignorance of the peeple</hi> joyned together; then they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented <hi>Purgatory, Maſſes, Prayer for the dead, works of Supererrogation, ſelling of Pardons,</hi> and all their other trinkets. For if they had not held our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers in ignorance, keeping them from the <hi>Word,</hi> they would never have been <hi>Papiſts</hi> But when they caſt a miſt before the eyes of all the People, then the <hi>blinde fell into that ditch,</hi> which doth contain ſo many <hi>groſs cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions.</hi> And you cannot but obſerve, that they are <hi>Coffer Doctrines,</hi> that <hi>Rome</hi> is moſt <hi>violent</hi> to juſtifie. <hi>Maſſes,</hi> which bring in <hi>maſſes of wealth; praying for the dead,</hi> which is a trick to <hi>prey upon the living;</hi> and ſo of ſelling <hi>Pardons,</hi> &amp;c. Yea what is the reaſon they <hi>forbid marriage,</hi> and commend <hi>vowes of chaſtity?</hi> but that they may with the more colour allow of <hi>Stews,</hi> and have <hi>large fees</hi> out of <hi>Harlots hiers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 10. All which miſcarriages, even of the <hi>Antichriſtian Prieſts,</hi> had been prevented, if the <hi>people</hi> would have afforded them, either plentifull, or indeed ſufficient maintenance. <hi>Learning</hi> would have more plentifull allowance, then other <hi>petty employments,</hi> or elſe it is in danger to be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous. For, if you obſerve it, where wit and poverty meet, they ſeldom make up an honeſt man. As what was the reaſon, that ſo many <hi>ſerpentine Preachers</hi> of the <hi>Prelaticall faction,</hi> were ſo eagerly driving towards <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> untill their <hi>mouthes</hi> were <hi>gag'd,</hi> their <hi>arms ſhortned,</hi> and their <hi>horns broken</hi> by the <hi>Parliament?</hi> but becauſe <hi>Popery</hi> is a trade, whereby they might become exceeding rich: yea their fingers itcht, and their teeth wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered after thoſe great revenues that are conferred upon the <hi>popiſh Clergy;</hi> and which their covetouſneſs and craft hath gained them. O that they had had no ſuch inducement! or that (ſince they have ſhewn themſelves ſo mercenary, and unfaithfull to him that put them in truſt,) they were all ſo ſerved. The <hi>Biſhops</hi> for their own ends brought them into the <hi>Church</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> of his mercy caſt them out, I mean all, as he hath already done ſome, that they may never return again: for if theſe <hi>Antichriſtian Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> be ſuffered, its impoſſible that ever the <hi>Church, or mens lives</hi> ſhould be <hi>reformed.</hi> Well may they obſtruct and hinder all that tends thereto.</p>
            <p>Yet nevertheleſſe, againſt reaſon, and all this experience, even in theſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169474:4"/>dayes of Goſpel-light, and ſo much means of Grace, they hold it as an <hi>Axiome;</hi> That to keep <hi>Miniſters</hi> poor, is the only way to make them ſtudy. Therefore they muſt be <hi>dieted like Horſes for a Race, not pampered.</hi> A <hi>fat Bird,</hi> ſay they, will not <hi>ſing;</hi> a <hi>fat Dog</hi> cannot <hi>hunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 11. Men will have a care, that <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſhall not be both wealthy and faithfull: rich and not true, or true and not rich; both together were a miracle. Whiles we had <hi>leaden Prieſts,</hi> we pay'd <hi>golden Tythes:</hi> and were then perſwaded, that <hi>blaſphemy</hi> and <hi>drunkenneſſe</hi> were <hi>tollerable</hi> ſins in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>ſacriledge.</hi> But now, thoſe that in our conſciences teach us the true way to bleſſedneſs, we think unworthy the worſt of what we have. To advance <hi>ſuperſtitious fopperies,</hi> the <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> think no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing too much. Wicked <hi>Athalia and her children, brake up the houſe of God, and all the things that were dedicated for his ſervice, they beſtowed upon Balim,</hi> 2 Cron. 24.7. <hi>Gods Prophets were glad of bread and water,</hi> whiles <hi>Jezabels four hundred trencher-Chaplains,</hi> were fed as daintily as the <hi>King</hi> himſelf. Should we have <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> and <hi>idolatrous Prieſts</hi> (as in <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi>) that more aym at the <hi>Churches goods,</hi> then the <hi>Churches good:</hi> at their <hi>own benefit</hi> more then the <hi>peoples profit,</hi> it were eaſie for them, to <hi>purchaſe</hi> both mens <hi>praiſes</hi> and <hi>purſes.:</hi> whereas every penny they part with, to a <hi>faithfull</hi> and <hi>painfull Paſtor,</hi> is drawn from them, as ſo many drops of bloud from the heart. As O the difference between theſe <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine dayes of the Goſpel,</hi> and the <hi>darkneſs of our Forefathers times:</hi> when even the comfortable uſe of the very <hi>Bible</hi> was interdicted them, the <hi>known language</hi> concealed, and they <hi>bound with a Curſe</hi> not to read it. Whereas now, it lyes open in our <hi>Churches,</hi> in out <hi>windowes:</hi> God grant we ſhut it not to our own <hi>ſouls.</hi> Which is mightily to be feared, if we cannot be at the leaſt coſt for our <hi>Religion;</hi> if we can be content to do <hi>God</hi> charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſervice.</p>
            <p>§. 12. It was gain that made <hi>Diana</hi> ſo great, and <hi>Demetrius</hi> to <hi>roar</hi> and make ſuch a tumultuous ſtir for her. Its far otherwiſe with our <hi>Miniſters;</hi> they beat their <hi>brains,</hi> and ſpend their <hi>ſpirits,</hi> pour out their <hi>prayers,</hi> plot and contrive all they can to ſave our poor <hi>ſouls:</hi> which being our caſe, what cauſe have we to fear the removall of our <hi>Candleſtick!</hi> and that <hi>God</hi> ſhould leave us in the dark, ſince we love <hi>darkneſs</hi> more then <hi>light:</hi> And to take away our faithfull <hi>Miniſters</hi> from us, when we ſo ill intreat them, and ſo unworthily reward them. If we preſume to <hi>coſen God, to purloyn the maintenance of his Miniſters,</hi> is not this to point <hi>God</hi> the way to plague us? and to ſend upon us <hi>a famine of preaching,</hi> who have brought <hi>a famine upon the Preachers?</hi> Is it not juſt with <hi>God,</hi> to take away the <hi>lamp</hi> from that <hi>Nation,</hi> which hath taken away the <hi>holy oyl</hi> that ſhould <hi>maintain</hi> it? And <hi>Lord</hi> I fear that <hi>England</hi> ſhall want the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> when the <hi>Barbarians</hi> receive it: becauſe <hi>England</hi> had the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and would not give a peny (more then forc't unto) to keep it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:169474:4"/>§. 13. And this (whatever carnall hearts conceive of it,) were <hi>a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er judgement, then the loſs of the Sun</hi> out of the <hi>firmament.</hi> A famine of bread is a ſore plague, when a wofull <hi>Mother, for her ſelf and ſon,</hi> is <hi>dreſſing their laſt proviſion.</hi> The extremity harder, when <hi>Mothers by turns cat up their own children,</hi> as it fell out, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.12. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 6.28. But this was nothing to <hi>a dearth of the Word.</hi> Even <hi>Seneca</hi> an <hi>Heathen</hi> could ſay, <hi>It is better not to be, then not to know. Better unborn then untaught.</hi> Which if true of <hi>humane knowledge,</hi> how much more of the <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel?</hi> For <hi>This is life eternall, to know the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent,</hi> John 17.3. And look to it my Brethren, leaſt you rob your ſelves and your poſterity to the worlds end, of injoying this <hi>matchleſs mercy,</hi> this <hi>unparralleld pearl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You indeed ſet a low price upon it, and thereafter deal with the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhers of it: but O what large bribes would <hi>Satan</hi> give to have ſuch men hold their peace, if they were of ſome <hi>great Lawyers</hi> minde? Yea I dare ſay, his ſervant the <hi>Pope</hi> would give them <hi>more to be ſilent,</hi> then you will willingly give them for all their <hi>pains in Preaching.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 14. <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are the <hi>Arms</hi> of the <hi>World, Counſellors</hi> the <hi>Brains, Lawyers</hi> the <hi>Tongues,</hi> the <hi>Rich</hi> the <hi>Stomacks,</hi> the <hi>Poor</hi> the <hi>Backs, Merchants</hi> the <hi>Feet, Officers</hi> the <hi>Hands,</hi> and <hi>Divines</hi> the <hi>Hearts. God</hi> made thee, thy <hi>Preacher</hi> (as a <hi>coworker together with God</hi>) ſaves thee. Where is another equivalent to <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Ambaſſador?</hi> And yet as if <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> had nothing to do with us, and nothing had done for us; there is none whom we ſo boldly defraud. Our beſt things ſhould not be too dear for the <hi>Lord,</hi> whoſe both they and our ſelves are. And thoſe that ſight for our ſouls, againſt <hi>ſpirituall powers,</hi> may challenge maintenance from us, and it is a ſhamefull unthankfulneſs to deny it. Nor do <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> more take pains then they pray for us. They <hi>beg</hi> and <hi>dig,</hi> and <hi>dig</hi> and <hi>beg,</hi> as that good <hi>Vine-dreſſer</hi> did, whoſe <hi>Mattock</hi> kept off the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters <hi>Ax,</hi> Luk. 13.8, 9. Beſides, he can never be truly <hi>thankfull to God,</hi> who is <hi>unthankfull to the means,</hi> by whom <hi>God</hi> doth him good.</p>
            <p>§. 15. When <hi>Abraham</hi> had <hi>vanquiſhed the five Kings,</hi> and delivered <hi>Lot</hi> and his family; <hi>the King of Salem met him with bread and wine.</hi> But we reward our <hi>Champions,</hi> that <hi>ſtand in the gap</hi> to defend us, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did <hi>Christ,</hi> they give us <hi>wine,</hi> and we return them <hi>vinegar.</hi> For either we tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, and ſpeak evil of them, as <hi>Abſolom</hi> did of his own <hi>father,</hi> 2 Sam. 15.3. Or we unjuſtly accuſe them, to get away their Livings, as <hi>falſe Ziba</hi> did <hi>honeſt Mephiboſheth.</hi> Or like <hi>Mules,</hi> we <hi>ſuck their milk,</hi> and then <hi>kick them with our heels,</hi> which is to outdo miſchief it ſelf. Yea ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it fares with them, as it did with the <hi>two milch Kine</hi> that carried the <hi>Ark of God</hi> back from the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> to <hi>Bethſhemiſh,</hi> that were for their labour burnt in ſacrifice, as ſoon as they had done that good office, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.14.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:169474:5"/>§. 16. But fare they well or ill, they go on in diſcharge of their duty, which proves them to be like the <hi>Apoſtles of Chriſt,</hi> who <hi>though they were beaten for Preaching in the Name of Jeſus, yet ceaſed they not to teach and preach the Gospel,</hi> and to win all they could, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.42. Indeed ſome there are that will ſquare cut their <hi>poſitions,</hi> according to their peoples <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,</hi> as not daring to ſpeak to the full extent of their <hi>conſciences,</hi> for fear leaſt by diſpleaſing their <hi>Auditory,</hi> they ſhould loſe their <hi>ſalary.</hi> Nor dare they reprove great mens particular ſins, becauſe ſuch an <hi>attempt</hi> would bring them into <hi>contempt.</hi> But how unlike are ſuch Meſſengers to <hi>Eliah,</hi> in his perſonall dealing with <hi>Ahab?</hi> to <hi>Eliſha,</hi> about <hi>Jehoram? Jeremiah,</hi> with <hi>Paſhur? Amos,</hi> with <hi>Amaziah? John Baptiſt,</hi> with <hi>Herod?</hi> our <hi>Saviour,</hi> with the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees? Steven,</hi> with the <hi>high Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Elders?</hi> yea S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> with <hi>Peter</hi> his fellow <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> and with <hi>Elymas the Sorcerer,</hi> moſt of them mighty and potent?</p>
            <p>And moſt pitifull is the caſe of ſuch a people, whoſe ſins are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived at, except <hi>conſcience</hi> makes a ſupply, which were extraordinary. Indeed if that be awake it will fear no man, but <hi>dares check a Magiſtrate, controul a Prince</hi> And admit it may ſometimes ſlumber (as no <hi>woman</hi> is alwaies <hi>ſcolding</hi>) yet when it wakes, it will ſpeak and ſpeak home.</p>
            <p>§. 17. But I ſpeak not of thoſe <hi>trencher Chaplains,</hi> who out of covete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and for want of courage, betray the truth; who are more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for their own profit and quiet, then of the <hi>peoples good,</hi> or <hi>Gods glory:</hi> for theſe were never ſent of <hi>God,</hi> and it's meet their <hi>wages</hi> ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their <hi>work:</hi> and yet I would rather erre in giving a <hi>Wolf</hi> his due (if he be appointed my Paſtor) then in the leaſt detain from a <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Shepherd</hi> what of right belongs to him.</p>
            <p>But I tell you of ſuch as fear <hi>God,</hi> and are of his ſending, who think it <hi>better</hi> to <hi>loſe mens favours then their ſouls,</hi> and will be ſure to diſcharge their conſciences from the burthen of any ones bloud. As <hi>Gods glory</hi> will make a good man <hi>speak,</hi> even when terrour it ſelf hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>ſilence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A conſcionable <hi>Miniſter</hi> reſembles <hi>David,</hi> who would venture on a <hi>Bear,</hi> rather then loſe a <hi>Lamb:</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> who would endure <hi>heat by day,</hi> and <hi>froſt by night,</hi> rather then neglect his <hi>flocks.</hi> And <hi>Moſes,</hi> who would fight with odds, rather then the <hi>Cattell</hi> ſhould <hi>periſh with thirſt.</hi> Only a <hi>Balaam</hi> wants this mercy.</p>
            <p>§. 18. And what though men remain obſtinate for a time? When wood is green, it will not preſently burn, yet if it be long blown, it will take fire, and flame at length. Or admit the worſt, yet he will not be ſilent. <hi>Good meat</hi> put into a <hi>ſtomack corrupt,</hi> feavouriſh, or <hi>hydropicall,</hi> doth not more nouriſh nature, then the diſeaſe: yet we do not thereupon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear utterly to give them meat, but rather ſtrive to purge out thoſe bad humours which cauſe the offence. The Lord by his Miniſters, gives every
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169474:5"/>of us <hi>light,</hi> let us beſeech him alſo for <hi>clear and ſound eyes,</hi> that we may finde benefit, and take comfort in the light he hath given us.</p>
            <p>§ 19. I grant, that in ſpeaking of this <hi>ſinfull ſin of Sacriledge,</hi> even the moſt conſcientious and faithfull <hi>Miniſters</hi> are too ſparing: Not for that <hi>Sacriledge</hi> ſcorns to be reprehended, nor for that he is taxed of indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that meddles with it, but that it may appear they leaſt of all ſeek themſelves. And for that they ſhould thereby ſo prejudice their hearers, that they would little regard what ever elſe they do deliver. For ſuch is the ſottiſhneſs and ſordidneſs of moſt men, which makes me the rather ſpeak; neither let any of theſe Godhaters, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30. blaſpheam the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> for what I have or ſhall ſpeak: For I am no <hi>Miniſter,</hi> nor have I any particular relation to the <hi>Miniſtry:</hi> ſo that ſelf-intereſt can bear no ſway with me, I only ſpeak my <hi>conſcience,</hi> as it is <hi>informed from the Word:</hi> And to me it repreſents it ſelf, as the moſt <hi>unjuſt, unreaſonable, ingratefull, abominable</hi> and <hi>prejudiciall ſin</hi> to our ſelves, of all other ſins.</p>
            <p>§.20. 1. Moſt <hi>unjuſt</hi> for <hi>we partake of the Preachers goods;</hi> they bring us the <hi>glad tidings of ſalvation,</hi> would furniſh and endow us with the <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, unvaluable, and laſting riches of grace and glory:</hi>) and ſhall not they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of <hi>our goods,</hi> that <hi>are inferiour, earthly and periſhing? Let him that is taught in the word, communicate unto him that teacheth, in all his goods,</hi> ſayes the Apoſtle,<hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. None but thoſe, who would <hi>give ſinne a paſport to offend,</hi> can deny this to be <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> and to be moſt <hi>just</hi> and <hi>equall.</hi> Yet to go home to that place, or to bring that place cloſe home to mens conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; would appear harſh, in theſe times of <hi>Goſpel light,</hi> or <hi>New-lights as they call them: if any man does not communicate, and communicate in all bis goods: God is not mockt,</hi> Gal. 6.7. ſo it falls, and I fear it falls heavy on many amongſt us. Again (ſaith the ſame <hi>Apoſtle,</hi>) <hi>If we have ſowen unto you ſpirituall things, is it a great thing if we reap yiur carnall things?</hi> 1 Cor. 9.11. <hi>Do ye not know, that they which miniſter about holy things, live of the things of the Temple; and they which wait at the Altar, are partakers with the Altar? Even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel:</hi> ver. 13, 14. He uſeth many other arguments in the ſame Chapter, that he may meet with <hi>mens carnal reaſonings</hi> in this caſe: As, <hi>Who goeth a warfare at any time at his own charges? who feedeth a flock, and eateth not of the milk of the flock?</hi> and the like, the which reade at your lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And in <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. <hi>Their debtors they are</hi> (which proves it not a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence or free gift,) <hi>for if the Gentiles have been made partakers of their ſpiritual things, their duty it alſo to minister unto them in carnal things,</hi> ver. 27. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calls it a <hi>debt,</hi> and tells us it is our <hi>duty:</hi> obſerve that. All which is <hi>New Teſtamens,</hi> if obſtinacy would ſuffer men to take notice of it. But <hi>our Phariſees</hi> are worſe then the <hi>Phariſces of old:</hi> for what ſaith one of the worſt of them? <hi>I pay tythes of all that I have:</hi> I ſhould have thought he had lied, but that <hi>our Saviour</hi> juſtifies him; even to <hi>mint and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169474:6"/>cummin. A Phariſce of Jeruſalem,</hi> was in this an <hi>honeſt man, to many Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of London<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> yet that <hi>Phariſee</hi> went to <hi>hell,</hi> in all probability.</p>
            <p>§. 21. Yea a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> muſt not require thoſe dues that are acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged (though perhaps thoſe dues will not maintain him;) but he is too ſtrict (eſpecially of the meaner ſort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>;) and yet ſometimes, and in ſome caſes, in loſing his right, he ſhall wrong and do prejudiee to other Paſtors that live about him, and thoſe likewiſe that ſhall ſucceed and come after him in his living: yea foſter his people in that fond conceit, of thinking their labour and miniſtry ſo little worth; which ought to be ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> would take money of his friends, though he car'd not for it, to teach them that it was his due, and how they ought to eſteem of the riches of the minde.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Why ſhould <hi>Miniſters</hi> more then other men, take a <hi>teſtern for a ſhilling?</hi> when themſelves that make the objection, will not think it fair dealing from their debtors, but take their full due, and think it neither breach of <hi>juſtice, piety</hi> or <hi>charity?</hi> why then ſhould they impoſe the ſame upon others?</p>
            <p>Fiftly, Admit he take his full due of a poor body; the pooreſt of all have ſouls; and I ſee not, but as the poor may count it a happineſs that they may have their <hi>mite</hi> accepted, ſo that the <hi>Miniſter</hi> in giving to the poor, ſhould have the ſame liberty that all men have, <hi>viz.</hi> to beſtow it where he pleaſeth, and where he thinks it will be beſt beſtowed. Briefly, if men would have Miniſters <hi>de jure cedere,</hi> they ſhould alſo learn <hi>jus red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</hi> But</p>
            <p>§. 22. 2. As it is moſt <hi>unjuſt,</hi> ſo it is moſt <hi>unreaſonable.</hi> Men would have <hi>fire</hi> kept in the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> but allow no <hi>fuel;</hi> they would have the <hi>lamp burn,</hi> but <hi>without oyl:</hi> And how do they ſerve <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>themſelves</hi> in ſo ſerving their <hi>Miniſters?</hi> To take away the <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vant</hi> from the <hi>Army,</hi> is to <hi>betray</hi> it to the <hi>Enemy:</hi> and ſimple ſouls, they do no leſs to their power, then <hi>split or ſink that ſhip in the midſt of the ſea, which alone ſhould ſave them. Sacriledge</hi> is the <hi>greateſt theft,</hi> yet of it men make the <hi>leaſt conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Merchant</hi> provides bravery for our <hi>backs,</hi> the <hi>Farmer</hi> food for our <hi>bellies,</hi> the <hi>Lawyer</hi> looks to our <hi>eſtates,</hi> the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> to our <hi>bodies,</hi> but th <hi>Divine</hi> ſaveth our <hi>ſouls;</hi> which is infinitely beyond all: For ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Gospel, Is not the life more worth then the meat, and the body then ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and the <hi>ſoul</hi> more pretious <hi>then all.</hi> And yet men envy not the prodigious wealth of <hi>Merchants,</hi> of <hi>Lawyers,</hi> of any: But they cannot hear of a <hi>Minister</hi> that hath a Tithe of their means, but their <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>ſplenes riſe</hi> at it: Yea this upon the point is the only conference, or parly, both in publick and private, how to <hi>decreaſe the Miniſters maintenance,</hi> and yet <hi>increaſe his work:</hi> which is like <hi>Pharaohs oppreſſing Gods people,</hi> Exod. 5. <hi>Get ye ſtraw where ye can finde it, yet ſhall nothing of your labour be diminiſhed.</hi> As good ſhat a <hi>Bird</hi> into a <hi>Cage,</hi> give her <hi>no meat,</hi> and yet bid her <hi>ſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:169474:6"/>§. 23. But what ſay they? Though we give them not ſo much as they would have, yet we give them ſufficient: Though not at does, yet as of benevolence and free gift Though this argument is held of no force in any other cafe. He that <hi>works</hi> with us by the day, we ſay is worthy of his <hi>wages,</hi> we do not call it a benevolence. Nor will the <hi>Lawyer</hi> or <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian</hi> give you thanks, though you tender unto them a more conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Fee,</hi> but for asking of aqueſtion. And are <hi>Divines</hi> ſlaves in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of all other men? Are <hi>thouſands</hi> but ſufficient for a <hi>Tradeſman,</hi> and an <hi>alms</hi> enough for a <hi>Minister?</hi> O that men would but reade what is written, <hi>Levit.</hi> 1.10. and 3.1. and 23.19. and 27.30, 32, 33. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14. 22, 23, 24, to 30. and 15.21. and 12.17, 18. and 17.1. And 26.12, to 16. <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.20, 21, 24. and 28.31. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 10.37, 38. <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.4.8. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.42. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.4. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.8, &amp;c. and 3.8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>Amos</hi> 4.4. <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. and 2. Chapters. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.22. and but ſeriouſly conſider of them.</p>
            <p>§. 24. But admit the ones <hi>humility</hi> ſhould ſatisfie the others <hi>pride,</hi> and take what they think ſufficient for <hi>Miniſter,</hi> and that as a benevolence, or free gift, and not as their own proper dues. What is it they call ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient? And what is their great benevolence, of which they are apt to boaſt, and for which they count him their ſervant? as their <hi>very children,</hi> by <hi>bearing their Parents diſcourſe,</hi> can in the <hi>School</hi> thus twit their <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> children, <hi>Your father</hi> is but <hi>our fathers ſervant,</hi> they maintain him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which to hear, though from fooliſh children, would make any good, or ingenuous mans bloud to riſe.</p>
            <p>Their contribution is even ſuch, as I am aſhamed to name, nor can I with patience once think of it. Perhaps the father of ſuch a childe gives to the <hi>Minister</hi> or <hi>Lecturer,</hi> if he be worth five hundred pounds, three pence a Quarter, as he gives to the <hi>Bclman,</hi> for labouring all the year like a <hi>Horſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Pariſhes</hi> that I could name, of late times, it's moſtly left to every mans choiſe, <hi>the more ſhame and pity,</hi> what he will give to the <hi>Minister,</hi> and what do they give? Not one in ten gives any thing, though many of them no mean ones,: yea ſome forſooth pretend <hi>conſcience</hi> for their robbing the <hi>Minister:</hi> he hath taken degrees, is ordained, is a blackcoat, a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> an <hi>Independent,</hi> will not indifferently adminiſter the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,</hi> nor give it men at home when they are ſick, as in former times; he had not their voice, nor conſent when he was choſen; or they do not like his Preaching, or he is a <hi>Roundhead,</hi> or I am of another <hi>Church,</hi> or I hear at other <hi>Churches,</hi> or I cannot edefie by his Preaching, or he <hi>preaches the Law,</hi> and therefore is a raylor, or the like. Of the reſt, the greater part give eight pence, twelve pence, or ſixteen pence a Year. And of thoſe that give two ſhillings, four ſhillings or more, there are not very many, though <hi>great Pariſhes,</hi> and the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> both <hi>Learned, Godly</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving:</hi> So that in <hi>Pariſhes</hi> where were 6 or 10 <hi>thouſand Communicants</hi> in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169474:7"/>the <hi>Biſhops</hi> time, there can ſcarce be collected clear to the <hi>Miniſter three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore pounds per annum,</hi> to maintain him, his wife and family, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide portions for his children.</p>
            <p>§. 25. And as for the <hi>Country,</hi> how many whole <hi>Pariſhes</hi> be there in the <hi>Land,</hi> yea how many hundreds, that ſuffer their <hi>faithfull and painfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter (who lies Ledger for the great King of Heaven and earth)</hi> to feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cruſts, and ſpin out <hi>twenty</hi> or <hi>fourty marks</hi> a year, into a thred as long as his life? Or if in other <hi>Pariſhes</hi> they allow their <hi>Miniſter</hi> more, is that more (if they can help it) any more then a mean <hi>Mechanick</hi> will get, with keeping <hi>two Apprentiſes, and a Journeyman,</hi> though he <hi>play himſelf.</hi> Or will their great benevolence afford a <hi>laborious Bee, books</hi> enough to furniſh his <hi>study,</hi> and breed his children as were fit, or provide them portions?</p>
            <p>Or if ſo, whereas men of other profeſſions, whether <hi>Attorneys, Shop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers, Aledrapers,</hi> &amp;.c. (not to name the richeſt, as <hi>Courtiers, Lawyers, Merchants</hi>) think it a ſmall matter, to get two or three hundred pounds a year, and leave their children five hundred or a thouſand pounds apiece to their portions. It is counted a mighty buſineſs, if a <hi>Miniſter</hi> hath an hundred, or ſixſcore pounds a year, which will not comfortably maintain his Charge, and afford him to do that good, which every one expects a <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhould do, have he never ſo little.</p>
            <p>Yea a <hi>Player, Fidler,</hi> or <hi>Dauncer</hi> is better maintained then a <hi>Preacher.</hi> And as if the <hi>better part</hi> were <hi>leaſt</hi> to be <hi>cared for,</hi> men could be content, if need were, to beſtow more upon a <hi>Licence to eat fleſh in Lent,</hi> then upon their <hi>ſouls all the year.</hi> Yea many mens <hi>ſhoeties</hi> coſt them more in a year, then <hi>God</hi> and <hi>their ſouls.</hi> And doth not all this ſpeak men moſt <hi>brutiſh</hi> and <hi>irrationall?</hi> yea <hi>impious</hi> and <hi>ungratefull?</hi> As <hi>God</hi> forbid men ſhould profit ſo little by their <hi>Miniſter,</hi> as their <hi>Miniſter</hi> profits by them.</p>
            <p>§. 26. And yet they have ſome peece of reaſon for it: for their blockiſh ſtupidity is ſuch, that they think none live more idely then <hi>Scholars:</hi> yea doubtleſs they think <hi>Ministers</hi> can preach without <hi>ſtudy</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did; or live by <hi>miracle</hi> as <hi>John Baptist</hi> did. Miſtake me not; I have no minde to meddle with that <hi>perverſe generation,</hi> that are ſo <hi>drunk</hi> with an <hi>opinion</hi> of the <hi>spirit;</hi> and ſuch <hi>enemies to learning,</hi> and pains in <hi>ſtudy,</hi> that they <hi>barrowcado their hearts,</hi> not only <hi>againſt the admitment</hi> of what any one of another judgement can <hi>attedge,</hi> but even againſt <hi>common ſenſe:</hi> though theſe alſo are of the others judgement, and that in the extreme. For theſe hold, yea will maintain, that <hi>a Cobler</hi> may ſit at his work all the week, and yet <hi>preach</hi> two better Sermons upon the <hi>Lords day</hi> ex tempore, then the <hi>beſt Scholar</hi> can do, that ſpends himſelf in his <hi>library,</hi> alledging the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> for their warrant. And yet could I hear <hi>Fiſhermen</hi> or the like, write and preach like the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and likewiſe <hi>ſpeak all Languages</hi> by the <hi>Spirit</hi> as they did; who of <hi>no Scholars</hi> were ſuddenly changed into <hi>greater Scholars</hi> and better <hi>Orators</hi> then ever the <hi>world</hi> bred up in the beſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities:</hi> I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169474:7"/>would ſee if I could prevail with my underſtanding, to ſubmit to their judgements. In the mean time I ſay, of all men in the world, I mean not to meddle with them, and I ſhould be as ſorry to have them meddle with me. And therein alſo my hope is depending, for like that <hi>Horſe</hi> ſent to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Butler</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> they care not for <hi>books,</hi> yea they will allow of <hi>no books</hi> to be <hi>read but the Bible</hi> (wherein by conſequence, they <hi>condemn all preaching.</hi>) So having a little ſtept out of my way, to meet with our <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſts,</hi> as once <hi>a grave Divine</hi> ſtept out of his text, to meet with <hi>King James</hi> about his <hi>ſwearing,</hi> I return to the parties with whom my buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs lies.</p>
            <p>§.27. Men envy not the prodigious wealth of <hi>Merchants, Lawyers, Courtiers;</hi> but they cannot hear of <hi>a Miniſter,</hi> that hath <hi>a tythe of their means,</hi> but their <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>ſplenes riſe at it.</hi> Nor muſt what they have be counted as <hi>due wages</hi> for their <hi>work;</hi> though as I ſhewed before, <hi>he that preacheth the Goſpel ſhould live of the Gospel,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.7, to 15. Thought <hi>he that is taught in the word, is commanded to communicate unto him that teacheth in all his goods,</hi> Gal. 6.6. Rom. 15.27. Though our <hi>debt</hi> and <hi>duty</hi> to our <hi>spiritual Paſtors</hi> is ſuch, as that <hi>Paul</hi> told <hi>Philemon, Thou oweſt unto me, even thine own ſelf,</hi> Philem. 19. And though the beleeving <hi>Galathians</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Paul</hi> as an <hi>Angel</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> yea even as <hi>Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> and to pleaſure him, <hi>would</hi> if it had been poſſible, <hi>have plucked out their own eyes and have given them unto him,</hi> Gal. 4.14, 15. But it muſt be called, <hi>a benevolence forſooth, or free gift.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 28. And in caſe he ſeeks to mend himſelf, by accepting of better means, they will make it ſuch a hainous matter, as if he had <hi>ſtolen a horſe;</hi> or as if he had <hi>forſaken his lawfull wife, and married another woman.</hi> As it, would amaze a man to hear, how confidently theſe blocks will maintain; that a <hi>Miniſter</hi> in this caſe, cannot with a good conſcience forſake his <hi>people,</hi> yea though his aym and end be principally the <hi>glory of God.</hi> As when all, or moſt in the <hi>Pariſh, blinde themſelves with prejudice</hi> againſt him, and even <hi>ſtop their ears</hi> againſt whatſoever truth he delivers, reſolving againſt their own converſion: If he ſhall remove to another people, that will <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him as the</hi> Galathians <hi>did</hi> Paul; and help them to another whom they far more reſpect, and whoſe Miniſtry is more likely to do good upon them: they will moſt baſely calumniate him, and not he alone ſhall ſuffer, but all theſe <hi>Churchmen</hi> ſay they, are ſo covetous, that they never think they have enough. And what <hi>hospitality</hi> do they keep? when they have ſcarce enough to fill the bellies of their own families: all which not only argues them as brainleſs as beaſts, but proves them to be as full of the <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents enmity,</hi> as the <hi>egge of a Cockatrice</hi> is full of <hi>poyſon.</hi> But.</p>
            <p>§. 29. 3. As it is moſt <hi>unjuſt</hi> and <hi>unreaſonable,</hi> ſo it is the moſt <hi>abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> in <hi>Gods</hi> ſight of all other ſins.</p>
            <p>How abominable it is, we may partly gather from the many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169474:8"/>and threatnings which <hi>God</hi> throughout all the <hi>old Teſtament</hi> ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for the <hi>robbing</hi> him of his <hi>Tythes, Offerings,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10, 11. and 1.7, 8, 13, 14. <hi>Hag.</hi> 1, and 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Chapters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, What is the <hi>root</hi> and <hi>spring of this their spight</hi> and <hi>enmity</hi> to the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> but an inbred enmity and hatred againſt <hi>God</hi> himſelf? As when <hi>Satan</hi> ſlew <hi>Jobs ſons</hi> and <hi>ſervants,</hi> his <hi>malice</hi> was againſt <hi>Job.</hi> Or as when <hi>Saul darted a ſpear at Jonathan,</hi> his <hi>spight</hi> was againſt <hi>David:</hi> He that loves not the <hi>members,</hi> was never a friend to the <hi>Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ 30. And accordingly <hi>God</hi> takes what is done to his <hi>Miniſters</hi> or <hi>Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> as done to himſelf. <hi>They have not caſt thee away,</hi> ſaith <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Samuel, but they have caſt me away, that I ſhould not reign over them,</hi> 1 Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 8.7. <hi>You are gathered together againſt the Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes,</hi> to <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram;</hi> when they preſumptuouſly told him, He and <hi>Aaron</hi> had taken too much upon them; and <hi>what is Aaron, that ye murmur againſt him?</hi> Num. 16. 11. <hi>He that hateth me,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, meaning as he was a Miniſter of the Goſpel, <hi>hateth my Father alſo,</hi> Joh. 15.23. which proves a world among us to be <hi>God-haters,</hi> Rom. 1.30. Many ſuch places I might <hi>alledge</hi> if I would be <hi>large.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If men <hi>honoured Chriſt</hi> they could not <hi>diſpiſe</hi> his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> his <hi>Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors:</hi> if they <hi>deſpiſe</hi> his <hi>Miniſters</hi> they do not <hi>honour Chriſt:</hi> and if they do not <hi>honour him</hi> he will never <hi>honour them.</hi> But it appears, that too-many <hi>value</hi> not their <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſo much <hi>as</hi> they do <hi>their Horſe,</hi> which is a ſign of a deſperate condition. When <hi>Homer</hi> had ſpent many lines in diſpraiſing the <hi>body of Therſites,</hi> he briefly deſcribes his ſoul thus; That he was <hi>an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Ulyſſes.</hi> And we need ſay no more of a bad man, then he is <hi>an enemy to his Paſtor,</hi> that <hi>is enough to brand him.</hi> But.</p>
            <p>§ 31. 4. It is not more <hi>unjuſt, unreaſonable,</hi> and <hi>abominable,</hi> then it is <hi>fooliſh</hi> and <hi>prejudiciall</hi> to our ſelves. For our ſelves ſuffer moſt, and are the greateſt looſers in this kinde of thriſt. As mark diligently I pray you, but theſe few Scriptures, <hi>Is it time for your ſelves to dwell in your ſeeled Houſes. and this my Houſe lie waſte,</hi> Hag. 1. <hi>Now therefore thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, Conſider your own waies; Ye have ſown much, and bring in little; ye eat, but ye have not enough; ye drink, but ye are not filled with drink; ye cloathe you, but ye are not warm; and he that earneth wages, putteth the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges into a bag with holes. Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, Conſider your waies in your hearts; and go up to the Mountain, and bring Wood, and build this Houſe; and I will take pleaſure in it, and I will be glorified in it, ſaith the Lord; Ye looked for much, and lo it came to little; and when ye brought it home, I did blow upon it; and why ſaith the Lord of Hosts? even becauſe of my Houſe that is waſte, and ye turn every man unto his own Houſe. Therefore the heaven ever you is ſtayed from dew, and the earth it ſtayed from her fruit: And I called for a drought upon the land, and upon the mountains, and upon the corn, and upon the corn, and upon the new wine, and upon the oyl, and upon all that the ground, bringeth forth, and upon men, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169474:8"/>upon cattell, and upon all the labour of the hands,</hi> Hag. 1.4. to 12.</p>
            <p>§. 32. And again in the ſecond Chapter, from the 15. verſ. <hi>And now I pray you conſider in your mindes from this day and upward, even afore a stone was laid upon a ſtone in the Temple of the Lord: ſince theſe daies were, when one came to an heap of twenty meaſures, there were but ten; when one came to the preſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat for to draw out fifty veſſels out of the preſſe, there were but twenty. I ſmote you with blaſting, and with mildew, and with hail in all the labours of your hands; yet you turned not to me, ſaith the Lord. Conſider I pray you in your mindes, from this day and upward, from the four and twentieth day of the ninth moneth, even from the day that the foundation of the Lords Temple was laid, conſider it in your mindes. Is the ſeed yet in the barn? yea, as yet the vine, and the fig-tree, and the Pomegranate, and the Olive-tree hath not brought forth: from this day will I bleſse you,</hi> Hag. 2.15, 16. to 20.</p>
            <p>And again, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. <hi>Will a man rob God? yet ye have robbed me, but ye ſay, wherein have we robbed thee? In tythes and offerings. Ye are curſed with a curſe, for ye have robbed me, even this whole Nation, Bring ye all the tythes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to the ſtorehouſe, that there may be meat in mine houſe, and prove me now here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, if I will not open the windows of Heaven unto you, and powr you out a bleſſing without meaſure, ſo that there ſhall not be room enough to receive it. And I will rebuke the devourer for your ſakes, and he ſhall not deſtroy the fruits of your ground, neither ſhall your Vine caſt her fruit before the time, or be barren in the field, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts. And all Nations ſhall call you bleſſed, for ye ſhall be a delightſom Land, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Mal. 3.8. to 13.</p>
            <p>By theſe places you may ſee, that <hi>if God be to be truſted,</hi> the only way to abound in all things, and to have them bleſt unto us, is to <hi>pay the Lord his dues;</hi> Whereas from them that will not <hi>pay the tenth,</hi> or a conſiderable part, <hi>he takes away,</hi> if not all <hi>the other nine,</hi> yet ſo much as may make us no ſmall looſers: A caſe worth the conſidering of <hi>all that ſtudy to be rich.</hi> Nor is it poſſible with words to expreſſe the truth of a thing more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, fully, and plainly, then the Lord hath delivered himſelf to us in the fore-mentioned Scriptures touching this point.</p>
            <p>§. 33. There was a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> well known and obſerved by many <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> and other <hi>conſciencious Chriſtians</hi> in this <hi>Land,</hi> that had the <hi>tythes of a Parſonage impropriate;</hi> by right whereof he demanded <hi>tythe wool</hi> of a <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioner</hi> who was <hi>very rich,</hi> and the owner of many hundred <hi>ſheep:</hi> he ſent him a very ſmall quantity, the <hi>ſervants</hi> ſhewed it their <hi>Maſter,</hi> the <hi>Maſter his neighbours,</hi> who all acknowledged that he did him wrong. He <hi>demanded</hi> more, the other <hi>denied</hi> to give more; and vowed in his <hi>choler,</hi> that if he were driven to pay more, he would never keep ſheep again, and ſo depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve him of that profit. The <hi>Law compelled him,</hi> whereupon <hi>he put away his ſheep:</hi> after which he <hi>preſently fell into ſuch decay,</hi> that when this <hi>Gentleman</hi> was <hi>burried</hi> (which was not long after,) <hi>he</hi> among the reſt of the poor
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169474:9"/>people, <hi>ſtood to receive ſuch almes as were given at the funerall.</hi> And this my ſelf can ſay out of experience; that in ſerving the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> when time was, I gained in a lawfull way many hundreds a year: but being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull, and not once intending to <hi>glorifie God</hi> with my ſubſtance; what I got, <hi>God</hi> did blow upon, and it was <hi>put into a bag with holes,</hi> as the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.6, 9. for my eſtate rather leſſened, then encreaſed: untill amongſt other things, I indented with my ſelf, to make conſcience of <hi>ſanctifying the Sabbath,</hi> and to return to the giver (as he ſhould direct,) the tythe of what I then was, or ever after ſhould be able to expend: whereupon I found ſuch a ſudden change, and that <hi>God</hi> did ſo bleſſe and proſper me, that it appeared miraculous! for no reaſon could I give of this his mercy, but his mercy <hi>and O the depth!</hi> Nor was this the one half: for as in a ſhort time, the <hi>Lord</hi> framed my eſtate to my minde; which made me leave off all publike employment, he hath ever ſince ſo framed my minde to my eſtate and preſent condition (which amounts to more then all the millions this world is worth,) that I think I may ſpeak it without vanity, there is not a man alive more brimfull of joy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. I know I ſhall be counted a fool for this: but if it may be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement to others, to <hi>truſt God,</hi> or <hi>at leaſt</hi> to <hi>try him, in making conſcience of this foul and conſuming ſin,</hi> it ſhall never trouble me. It is a happy loſs that makes <hi>God</hi> and his Church gainers.</p>
            <p>§. 34. I will take leave to cloſe this diſcourſe with <hi>a double ſute;</hi> one to the <hi>people</hi> in generall, the other to <hi>ſupream Authority:</hi> both which ſhall come from an heart unfainedly devoted to the <hi>common good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My ſuit to the firſt of theſe is: that what hath been ſpoken may be an inducement to <hi>all that have any fear of God, or love of their own ſouls, to try the ſucceſs of paying to Miniſters their due:</hi> I ſpeak not to the <hi>prophane,</hi> for who can wonder that thoſe men <hi>diſregard their Ministers</hi> that have <hi>caſt off all reſpect of God and their own ſouls.</hi> Neither do I need to preſſe ſuch whoſe <hi>hearts</hi> are <hi>changed</hi> by the power of their <hi>Paſtors preaching.</hi> For great is the affection of a <hi>Convert,</hi> to the Miniſtry which hath been the <hi>means of his converſion: He accounts his very eyes but a mean recompence for ſo great a benefit,</hi> Gal. 4.15 Yea, our debt and duty to our <hi>ſpiritual Paſtors</hi> is ſuch, as that <hi>Paul</hi> told <hi>Philemon, Thou oweſt unto me even thine own ſelf.</hi> And the <hi>Primitive times</hi> prove it; inſomuch that <hi>Luther</hi> ſayes, ſo ſoon as the <hi>Goſpel</hi> took <hi>root in mens hearts,</hi> and after when it <hi>revived again, money grew dead.</hi> The <hi>glad tydings of the Goſpel,</hi> was <hi>ſo ſweet</hi> to them, that in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, <hi>riches had no relliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 35. I ſpeak not unto theſe, I ſay, but to ſuch as have not hitherto made conſcience of this duty: and all ſuch I beſeech as they tender the good of their <hi>eſtates here,</hi> and their <hi>ſouls hereafter,</hi> to <hi>take</hi> Gods <hi>word;</hi> As what heart is able to ſtand out, when he hears and conſiders what the <hi>Lord</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. <hi>Do but try me, ſaith the Lord, if I will not pour out a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169474:9"/>bleſſing upon you,</hi> &amp;c. ver. 10, &amp;c. Count it not <hi>loſt,</hi> what you give to your <hi>Paſtor:</hi> think it not <hi>gotten</hi> what you <hi>gull</hi> him of. Give him not the <hi>ſtarve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of your breed;</hi> the <hi>beſt of all</hi> kindes, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it to be conſecrated to the <hi>Lord of all.</hi> Every thing we have is <hi>too good for us,</hi> if we think any thing we have <hi>too good for him.</hi> Say not with <hi>Judas, why is this waſte?</hi> but with <hi>David, I will not offer to the Lord of that which cost me nothing,</hi> 2 Sam. 24.24. And by <hi>maintaining your Paſtors body,</hi> he is inabled the better to <hi>feed your ſouls.</hi> When the <hi>lamp</hi> is not fed with <hi>oyl,</hi> there will be but a <hi>dark houſe.</hi> Yea ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your <hi>Miniſter</hi> growes <hi>old;</hi> and be no longer able, or fit to feed your ſouls with <hi>ſpirituall manna;</hi> caſt him not off: but maintain him and his charge, according to his former pains and deſerving. Yea, let not his <hi>wife and children want,</hi> though he be <hi>dead.</hi> Occaſion not the world, to laugh at the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> or his, when they come to beg <hi>a ſtraw</hi> of their <hi>own ſheaf.</hi> The <hi>Levite might not ſerve after fifty.</hi> What then? muſt he loſe his main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance? no, he <hi>had the ſame proviſion ſtill.</hi> A man will not <hi>caſt off his Dog being old,</hi> becauſe he hath a <hi>long time done him ſervice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 37. Secondly, My ſure to <hi>Soveraign Authority</hi> is: that they will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> may be ſo <hi>maintained;</hi> if not by the <hi>name of Tythes,</hi> (which name only is <hi>made a colour to coſen the Clergy of all:</hi>) yet at leaſt in ſome other way; that they may live comfortably, without carking or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what they ſhall do, and where they ſhall get their bread, when their own temporall means is gone. The <hi>Lord</hi> hath committed the <hi>ſouls of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates</hi> to their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> but the <hi>bodies of Minsters</hi> to the <hi>Magiſtrates.</hi> And indeed what ſhould become of the <hi>Levites,</hi> if there were not <hi>Laws:</hi> and what of the <hi>Church</hi> if there were no <hi>Levites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 38. And ſo much of <hi>contemning and robbing Chriſts Ambaſſadours</hi> of the <hi>Miniſtry;</hi> which is enough to prove, that <hi>Millions</hi> who <hi>think they love God, do indeed,</hi> and in good earneſt <hi>hate him</hi> (For our <hi>love to God</hi> is beſt <hi>known by our</hi> reſpect to, and <hi>uſage of his Meſsengers,</hi>) Of wronging and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them in their perſons and good names; which follows in the <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed copy;</hi> together with the reſidue of <hi>Englands ſinne and unthank fulneſs;</hi> when the <hi>Stationer</hi> ſhall be encouraged by the acceptance that theſe finde, which are already done, to print the <hi>whole in a larger character;</hi> which may well be doubted, in that men are ſo taken up with <hi>News</hi> and <hi>Controverſie,</hi> (a, new <hi>trick of the devils</hi>) that few read <hi>profitable Divinity:</hi> or if ſo, not many can hear theſe downright truths; but they muſt alſo hear the <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> of their own <hi>condemnation.</hi> Wherefore for the interim, If any out of a <hi>publike spirit,</hi> would have many of theſe without coſt (to <hi>diſtribute</hi> to whom they concern) let them repair to the <hi>Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Part.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Abraham Miller</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>James Crump</hi> in Little <hi>Bartholmewes Well-yard.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
